摄影师经常提到一种叫做色温的东西;色温
Photographers frequently refer to something called color temperature; color temperature
正在谈论他们正在研究的光谱
is saying something about the spectrum of the light that they are looking at in terms
相当于黑体散热器。所以与这个夕阳红相关的光谱
to the equivalent black body radiator. So the spectrum associated with this red sunset
相当于一个约2000至3000度开尔文的黑体辐射体。它是一个
is equivalent to a black body radiator of about 2000 to 3000 degrees kelvin. It is a
非常微红的光。钨灯相当于约3000左右的色温
very reddish light. A tungsten light is equivalent to a color temperature of around about 3000
开尔文。中午的太阳光谱相当于黑色的身体散热器
kelvin. The spectrum of the sun at midday is equivalent to a black body radiator of
大约5000到5400开尔文。摄影师会说阳光比较蓝
around 5000 to 5400 kelvin. A photographer would say that the sunlight is bluer then
钨灯，或者我们可以说钨灯比正午的阳光更红。
the tungsten light, or we can say tungsten light is more red then the midday sun.
在阴天的情况下，色温实际上甚至更高
In the case of an overcast day, the color temperature is, in fact, even higher, the
世界上的点不再被来自太阳的白光照亮，它被照亮了
point in the world is no longer illuminated by the white light from the sun, it is illuminated
来自天空的蓝光和光线中过量的蓝光相当
by the blue light from the sky and this excess amount of blue in the light is equivalent
一个更热，更热的黑体散热器。所以摄影师会将此称为
to a much, much hotter black body radiator. So a photographer would refer to this as a
色温在8000到10000开尔文范围内。
color temperature in the range 8000 to 10 000 kelvin.
我们的太阳在太空中是一个非常热的物体，并且起到黑体散热器的作用，但是
Our sun is a very hot object in space and functions as a black body radiator, but by
来自太阳的光线发现光谱的地面水平的时间
the time the light from the sun finds its way down to ground level the spectrum has
被大幅改变，这是因为大气中的一些化学物质-我们
been dramatically altered and that is because of a number of chemicals in the atmosphere — we
有臭氧，氧气，水，二氧化碳等-每一个都去掉了部分
have ozone, oxygen, water, carbon dioxide and so on — and each of them remove parts
来自太阳的辐射所以当光线到达地面时
of the radiation that comes from the sun. So by the time the light gets to the ground
光谱与理想的黑体辐射器略有不同。最高峰
the spectrum is a little bit different from an ideal black body radiator. The peak of
到达地面时光的光谱大约是
the spectrum of a light by the time it reaches the ground is around about
550纳米......它有点绿色，毫不奇怪，这就是颜色
550 nanometers … it is a little green color and, not surprisingly, that is the color that
我们的眼睛最敏感。很多来自黑色的能量
our eyes are most sensitive to. A lot of the energy that comes from a black
在我们在这些较长波长中看不到的部分光谱中发射体辐射体，
body radiator is emitted in parts of the spectrum that we cannot see in these longer wavelengths,
这是这些钨灯泡被逐步淘汰的原因之一。
and this is one of the reasons that these tungsten light bulbs are being phased out.
它们将一些电能转换成我们可以看到的光，但它们会转换
They convert some of the electrical energy into light that we can see, but they convert
太多的热量，这无助于我们看到。他们并不特别
an awful lot of it into heat which does not help us to see. They are not particularly
高效。所以有很多能量被释放出来
efficient. So there is a lot of energy being emitted
在这些较长的波长，所以如果我们在这里看一下这个光谱，我们可以看到
at these longer wavelengths, so if we look at this spectrum here, we can see that the
光谱的可见部分，实际上是400到700纳米之间的区域
visible part of the spectrum, that region between 400 and 700 nanometers, is actually
整个电磁频谱的一小部分。
a very small part of the overall electromagnetic spectrum.
凭借我们的眼睛，我们能够在这个非常狭窄的部分感受到电磁辐射
With our eyes we are able to sense electromagnetic radiation in this very narrow part of the
整体频谱。虽然我们看不到红外线辐射，
overall spectrum. Although we cannot see infra-red radiation,
我们仍然可以感受到它，我们可以感受到它的温暖，就像我们皮肤上的温暖。红外辐射
we can still sense it and we can feel it as heat, as warmth on our skin. Infra-red radiation
早在18世纪，德国出生的英国天文学家威廉·赫歇尔就发现了这一点。他建造
was discovered by William Herschel, a German-born English astronomer back in the 1700s. He built
一个巨大的望远镜，发现了许多恒星和行星。
an enormous telescope and discovered many stars and planets.
有一天，他从望远镜上取下光线，将棱镜穿过一张桌子
And one day he took the light from his telescope passed it through a prism onto a table and
他把温度计放在桌子上的不同频谱部分。他在努力
he put a thermometer into different parts of the spectrum on the table. He was trying
测量蓝色和黄色以及紫色和红色的温度。
to measure the temperature of blue and yellow and violet and red.
令他感到惊讶的是，当他把温度计放在桌子的一个区域时
And what surprised him was that when he put the thermometer into an area of the table
在他看不到任何光线的地方，温度计仍记录着高温，所以那里
where he couldn’t see any light, the thermometer still recorded a high temperature, so there
是加热温度计的辐射，但是他无法看到它，所以他发现了
was radiation that was heating the thermometer but he was unable to see it, so he discovered
红外辐射。他称之为热量射线。
infra-red radiation. He referred to them as calorific rays.
我之前提到过，我们可以将红外辐射感知为热量。有些设备叫做
I mentioned before that we can sense infra-red radiation as heat. There are devices called
热像仪，它们对所谓的红外辐射非常敏感
thermal cameras and they are very sensitive to this infra-red radiation in what is called
9到14微米之间的热或长红外波段。
the thermal or long infra-red band between 9 and 14 micrometres.
那是9000到14000纳米，我们之前使用的单位。
That is 9000 to 14 000 nanometers, the units that we were using previously.
在这部分频谱中，人类会释放能量，因此你可以看到那些人
And in that part of the spectrum human beings emit energy, and so you can see that people
这里温暖的背景是温暖的。这是我们的自然体温，37度
here are warm against a colder background. This is our natural body temperature, 37 degrees
摄氏度，这意味着我们自己是黑体辐射器，我们发射不多
Celsius, it means that we ourselves are black body radiators and we are emitting not much
但是少量的红外线能量和热像仪可以
but a small amount of infra-red energy and a thermal camera can
拿起来。热像仪通常用于诊断建筑物的热量损失;该
pick this up. Thermal cameras are often used to diagnose heat loss from buildings; the
在建筑物外面应该是凉爽的，但如果有热点，它通常会倾向于
outside of a building should be cool, but if there are hot spots it generally tends
表明建筑物内部的热量泄漏到外面的世界。
to indicate the heat is leaking from inside the building to the outside world.
火甲虫对红外辐射非常敏感。它喜欢产卵
The fire beetle is exquisitely sensitive to infra-red radiation. It likes to lay its eggs
到烧焦的树木，所以它去寻找森林火灾，并采用特殊的红外线
into burnt trees, so it goes hunting for forest fires and to do that it uses special infra-red
感应器官内置于胸腔内。还有大量非黑人
sensing organs built into its thorax. There are also a large number of non-black
人体照度：例如，发光二极管具有光谱特性
body illuminance: light emitting diodes, for instance, have got a spectral characteristic
像这样形状与黑体发射光谱形状完全不同，所以我们可以这样做
like this quite differently shaped to the black body emission spectrum, so here we can
看到蓝色LED，绿色LED和红色LED的发射。
see the emission of a blue LED, a green LED and a red LED.
我们看到能量集中在一个相当窄的光谱带中。没有浪费
We see that the energy concentrated into a fairly narrow spectral band. There is no wasting
例如，在光谱的红外部分发射。
or emission in the infra-red part of the spectrum, for instance.
紧凑型荧光灯管的光谱非常复杂：光线是混合光
A compact fluorescent tube has got a very complex spectrum: the light is a mixture of
由大量不同荧光粉发出的光，白色层内部为螺旋形
the light emitted by a large number of different phosphors, the white layer inside the helical
被气体放电激发的管子。因此每种荧光粉都会发出不同的光
tube which is excited by the gas discharge. So each phosphor emits light at a different
波长。我们认为这些不同波长的整体组合
wavelength. The overall combination of these different wavelengths appears to our eye to
是白色的。另一种非黑体发光是激光;激光可能有点
be white. Another non-black body illuminate is the laser; the laser is perhaps somewhat
类似于我们刚才看到的发光二极管，除了光谱
similar to the light emitting diode that we looked at a moment ago, except that the spectrum
非常狭窄。最后，这些是与红色相关的镜面发射，
is extremely narrow. Finally, these are the specular emissions associated with the red,
在旧式阴极射线管中的绿色和蓝色荧光粉，这显示了发射
green and blue phosphors in an old fashion cathode ray tube and this shows the emission
蓝色荧光粉的光谱，此曲线在这里;绿色荧光粉，这条曲线在这里;
spectrum of the blue phosphor, this curve here; the green phosphor, this curve here;
和含有大量相当窄带发射的红色荧光粉，但是
and the red phosphor which contains a large number of quite narrow band emissions, but
它们一起在人眼看来是红色的。
together collectively they appear to the human eye as red.
正如我刚才提到的那样，到达地球表面的光是部分的
As I mentioned a moment ago, the light that reaches the surface of the planet is partly
被地球大气层中的各种分子吸收。特别是水是一种
absorbed by various molecules in the atmosphere of the planet. Water, in particular, is a
非常强大的光吸收。该图显示了光的吸收量
very strong absorber of light. This graph shows the amount of absorption of light as
波长的函数，我们可以看到有一个光谱区域
a function of wavelength and we can see that there is a region of the spectrum where there
是最小的光吸收。如果我们只看可见光带然后标记蓝色和
is minimal light absorption. If we look just at the visible band and then mark blue and
红色我们可以看到红光比蓝光吸收更多，这就解释了为什么，
red we can see that red light is absorbed more than blue light and this explains why,
当你在水下时，你越往水下，光线就会越来越多
when you are under water and the further you go under water, the light has got much more
对它的蓝色色调-你往往会失去红色和绿色等颜色，它们往往会消失
of a blue tint to it — you tend to lose colors like red and green, they tend to disappear
一切都开始变蓝，因为只有蓝光才能穿透
and everything starts to look blue because only the blue light is able to penetrate through
一大堆水。因此，让我们总结一下：我们拥有来自光源的光
a big column of water. So let’s summarise: we have light that comes from an illuminant
并且它产生场景的照度，我们可以根据它来描述光
and it produces illuminance of the scene and we can describe that light in terms of its
频谱，所以我们使用符号E来表示亮度，它是一个函数
spectrum, so we use the symbol E to represent the luminance and it is a function of the
波长，我们看了各种各样的照度，我们看了黑体
wavelength, and we have looked at various sorts of illuminance, we looked at black body
散热器，发光二极管，紧凑型荧光灯管和激光器
radiators, light emitting diodes, compact fluorescent tubes and lasers, each of these
有不同的光谱特征。
have got a different spectral characteristic.